Guide to the Yvonne Rainer Grand Union performance videotape collection MSS.174
Fales Library and Special Collections
Yvonne Rainer Grand Union Performance Videotape Collection
1972
Fales Library and Special Collections
Rainer, Yvonne, 1934-
MSS.174
4.5 Linear Feet
The collection consists of seven videotapes which document a series of Grand Union performances that took place on May 28, 1972 at the Joe LoGiudice Gallery at 59 Wooster Street in SoHo.
Provenance
The videotapes were donated to the Fales Library by Yvonne Rainer in 2002.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Historical Note
The Grand Union was a collective of nine choreographers/ dancers who performed group improvisations from 1970 to 1976. The group evolved out of work by Yvonne Rainer, in particular, Continuous Project-Altered Daily, yet Rainer purposefully subverted her role as leader; each member had an equal give-and-take in the creation and process of the performance. The Grand Union embraced dance, theater, and theatrics in an ongoing investigation into the nature of dance and performance. Performers included David Gordon, Stephen Paxton, Barbara Dilley, Nancy Lewis, Lincoln Scott, Becky Arnold and Douglas Dunn.
Grand Union's performances included both spontaneous and choreographed behaviors-using gesture, dance and voice-manipulating objects or bodies as objects, accompanied by a loosely constructed soundtrack of contemporary songs, music and silence. As Sally Banes writes in Terpsichore in Sneakers, "Just as their concerns varied, the persona each member of the Grand Union projected in performance could shift enormously from one night to the next, from one section of a single performance to another… widely divergent styles and concerns, working within a framework that encouraged provocation, as well as cooperation." Each performance was unpredictable, unrepeatable and ephemeral.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of seven videotapes which document a series of Grand Union performances that took place on May 28, 1972 at the Joe LoGiudice Gallery at 59 Wooster Street in SoHo. The performers are Trisha Brown, Barbara Dilley, Douglas Dunn, David Gordon, Nancy Green, Steve Paxton, and Yvonne Rainer. The original footage was shot on ½" open reel videotape by Gary Bower, Ron Clark, and Jamie Dearing and produced by Carlota Schoolman. In the late 1970's, Schoolman made ¾" U-Matic dubmasters of the original reels. In a letter to Yvonne Rainier, Schoolman suggested that this second set was incomplete, "missing the second half," possibly because she sent a tape to someone in London. In 1992, Middlemarch Films made another set of ¾" U-Matic dubs from the dubmasters for a documentary on postmodern dance. The material was not used in the documentary because of objections from Trisha Brown and Steve Paxton. In 2002, this set was given to the Fales Library and Special Collections by Yvonne Rainer. Preservation masters and research copies of the 7 tapes were made in April 2003 by Vidipax (Job #3947). Original numbering of tapes, eg. #D222, was applied by Middlemarch Films. Fales Media Object ID numbers, eg. #174.0001, were assigned in October 2005.
Arrangement
Material is arranged according to preexisting numerical order. Tape 2 was not part of acquisition.
Missing Title
Series I: Video recordings - The Grand Union, May 1972
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
Robert Alexander Papers (MSS.114)
Judson Memorial Church Archive (MSS.094)
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
New York (N.Y.).; Dance -- United States.; Modern dance.; Videocassettes.; Clark, Ron; The Grand Union; Brown, Trisha, 1936-2017; Paxton, Steve; Dilley, Barbara; Schoolman, Carlota; Gordon, David, 1936-; Dunn, Douglas, 1942-; Bower, Gary, 1940-; Dearing, Jamie; Green, Nancy
- Series I: Video recordings - The Grand Union, May 1972
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains all video materials in collection. Each subsequent tape is a contuation of the one previous constituting a single performance. Tape 2 was not part of acquisition.
  - Subseries A: Video recordings
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Subseries A includes original donated 3/4" Umatic tapes.
    - The Grand Union, Tape 1, May 1972; ID: 174.0001 (Box 1, Case 174.0001, Case 174.0022)
      Scope and Content
      Documentation of May 1972 dance performance by the Grand Union.
      Existence and Location of Copies
      DVD access copy available.
      Conditions Governing Access
      Currently available.
      Black & White, Sound
      Duration: 1 hour 2 minutes
      Original format: 3/4" Umatic
    - The Grand Union, Tape 3, May 1972; ID: 174.0004 (Box 1, Case 174.0004, Case 174.0023)
      Duration: 1 hour 1 minute
    - The Grand Union, Tape 4, May 1972; ID: 174.0007 (Box 1, Case 174.0007)
      Duration: 10 minutes
    - The Grand Union, Tape 5, May 1972; ID: 174.0011 (Box 1, Case 174.0011)
      Duration: 59 minutes
    - The Grand Union, Tape 6, May 1972; ID: 174.0013 (Box 1, Case 174.0013, Case 174.0024)
      Duration: 32 minutes
    - The Grand Union, Tape 7, May 1972; ID: 174.0016 (Box 1, Case 174.0016)
    - The Grand Union, Tape 8, May 1972; ID: 174.0020 (Box 1, Case 174.0020, Case 174.0025)
      Documentation of May 1972 dance performance by the Grand Union. Includes almost twenty minutes of after show footage.
      Duration: 58 minutes
  - Subseries B: Video Preservation Masters - CLOSED
    CLOSED
    - ID: 174.0002 - 174.0020 (Box PM 48)